Newton, Mass. First Church records, 1664-1974.
Congregational Library & Archives
- Financial records, 1708 1974; 1708-1974; 54 Folders; 29 Volumes
  - Building records, 1785 1974; 1785-1974; 22 Folders; 5 Volumes
    - Building committee records, 1902 1906; 1902-1906 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Church property records, 1896 1956; 1896-1956 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Church photographs, circa 1900 (Box 22, Folder 20)
    - 5th meeting house interior photographs, circa 1900 (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - 6th meeting house cornerstone and construction photographs, 1901 1909; 1901-1909 (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - 5th meeting house deconstruction photographs, 1902 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Memorial window fund, 1912 1914; 1912-1914 (Box 7, Volume 12)
    - Church additions, 1912 1953; 1912-1953 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Groundbreaking photographs, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 24)
    - 6th meeting house interior photographs, circa 1960 (Box 22, Folder 25)
    - Dispositions of church property, 1972 1974; 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 6th meeting house exterior photographs, undated (Box 22, Folder 26)
    - 6th meeting house glass plate negatives, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Pew records, 1805 1902; 1805-1902; 8 Folders; 7 Volumes
    This sub-series contains records relating to pews and pew owners and includes pew ledgers, correspondence, pew bills of sales, and records related to the use and maintenance of the horse shed.
    - Pews: correspondence, 1805 1886; 1805-1886 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Pew deeds, 1806 1852; 1806-1852 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Pew deeds, 1847 1852; 1847-1852 (Box 8, Volume 7)
    - Pewholders and stockholders records, 1846 1855; 1846-1855 (Box 12, Volume 2)
    - Proprietors records, 1855 1883; 1855-1883 (Box 12, Volume 3)
    - Proprietors records, 1883 1895; 1883-1895 (Box 12, Volume 4)
    - Pew plans and valuations, 1847 1888; 1847-1888 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Horse shed rentals, 1857 1894; 1857-1894 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Proprietor's pew ledger, 1863 1870; 1863-1870 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Proprietor's pew accounts, 1868 1896; 1868-1896 (Box 12, Volume 5)
    - Pew bills of sales, 1870 1902; 1870-1902 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Proprietor's pew ledger, 1870 1902; 1870-1902 (Box 12, Volume 6)
    - Pew accounts and cash book, 1876 1895; 1876-1895 (Box 12, Volume 7)
    - Materials from proprietors records, 1883-1895 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Pew and horse shed payments, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Auxiliary groups, 1854 1974; 1854-1974; 27 Folders; 69 Volumes
  This series contains records from auxiliary groups and committees from the First Church in Newton. Included in this series are meeting minutes, scrapbooks, financial records, bulletins, annual reports, and a cook book.
  - Sunday School, 1854 1924; 1854-1924; 1 Folder; 12 Volumes
    This sub-series contains records related to the operation of the Sunday school and includes superintendent's records and attendance records.
    - Sunday school records, 1854 1866; 1854-1866 (Box 13, Volume 14)
    - Sunday school records, 1867 1882; 1867-1882 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1867 1868; 1867-1868 (Box 13, Volume 15)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1868 1869; 1868-1869 (Box 13, Volume 16)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1870 1874; 1870-1874 (Box 13, Volume 17)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1872 1874; 1872-1874 (Box 14, Volume 1)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1875 1877; 1875-1877 (Box 14, Volume 2)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1878 1880; 1878-1880 (Box 14, Volume 3)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1880 1881; 1880-1881 (Box 14, Volume 4)
    - Sunday school superintendent's record book, 1883 1885; 1883-1885 (Box 14, Volume 5)
    - Sunday school attendance records, 1873 1876; 1873 (Box 14, Volume 6)
    - Sunday school primary department attendance records, 1916 1923; 1916-1923 (Box 14, Volume 7)
    - Sunday school junior department attendance records, 1921 1924; 1921-1924 (Box 14, Volume 8)
  - Women's Benevolent and Church Aid Society, 1861 1974; 1861-1974; 14 Folders; 29 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the records of the Women's Benevolent and Church Aid Society. The group was originally known as the Ladies Benevolent and Church Aid Society and in its later years was frequently simply called the Women's Benevolent Society. This sub-series includes meeting minutes, financial records, histories, a cook book, and constitutions.
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1861 1883; 1861-1883 (Box 14, Volume 15)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1864 1898; 1884-1898 (Box 14, Volume 16)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1893 1902; 1893-1902 (Box 14, Volume 17)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1899 1904; 1899-1904 (Box 15, Volume 1)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1902 1907; 1902-1907 (Box 15, Volume 2)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1905 1911; 1905-1911 (Box 15, Volume 3)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1907 1917; 1907-1917 (Box 15, Volume 4)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society records, 1911 1917; 1911-1917 (Box 15, Volume 5)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1915 1928; 1915-1928 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1916 1928; 1916-1928 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1917 1921; 1917-1921 (Box 15, Volume 6)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1917 1931; 1917-1931 (Box 15, Volume 7)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1918 1924; 1918-1924 (Box 15, Volume 8)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1921 1926; 1921-1926 (Box 15, Volume 9)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1926 1931; 1926-1931 (Box 15, Volume 10)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1931 1936; 1931-1936 (Box 15, Volume 11)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1936 1940; 1936-1940 (Box 15, Volume 12)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1940 1946; 1940-1946 (Box 15, Volume 13)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1946 1954; 1946-1954 (Box 15, Volume 14)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1954 1959; 1954-1959 (Box 15, Volume 15)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1959 1964; 1959-1964 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Women's Benevolent Society records, 1965 1972; 1965-1972 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Ladies Benevolent Society Church Aid Department financial records, 1894 1920; 1894-1920 (Box 15, Volume 16)
    - Women's Benevolent Society financial records, 1896 1908; 1896-1908 (Box 16, Volume 1)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society treasurer's account, 1899 1930; 1899-1930 (Box 11, Volume 3)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society Home Missionary Department financial records, 1905 1920; 1905-1920 (Box 16, Volume 2)
    - Ladies' Benevolent Society Local Charity General Expense Fund financial records, 1910 1920; 1910-1920 (Box 16, Volume 3)
    - Women's Benevolent Society financial records, 1920 1926; 1920-1926 (Box 11, Volume 4)
    - Women's Benevolent Society financial records, 1926 1933; 1926-1933 (Box 11, Volume 5)
    - Women's Benevolent Society treasurer reports, 1933 1974; 1933-1974 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Women's Benevolent Society financial records, 1959 1971; 1959-1971 (Box 16, Volume 7)
    - Women's Benevolent Society histories, 1909 1974; 1909-1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Women's Benevolent Society constitutions, 1914 1958; 1914-1958 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Women's Benevolent Society yearbooks, 1917 1971; 1917-1971 (Box 24)
    - Women's Benevolent Society bequests, 1924 1973; 1924-1973 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Women's Benevolent Society dues and pledges, 1928 1937; 1928-1937 (Box 16, Volume 4)
    - Women's Benevolent Society dues and pledges, 1930 (Box 16, Volume 5)
    - Greetings from Shanghai, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Choice Recipes from Members and Friends of the Women's Benevolent Society, 1939 (Box 16, Volume 6)
    - Women's Benevolent Society annual reports, 1956 1968; 1956-1968 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Women's Benevolent Society officers and constitution, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Women's Benevolent Society pamphlets and musical, 1969 1973; 1969-1973 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Diposition of Women's Benevolent Society assets, 1971 1974; 1971-1974 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Benevolence Committee, 1870 1954; 1870-1954; 1 Folder; 7 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the financial records of the Benevolence Committee.
    - Benevolence financial records, 1870 1888; 1870-1888 (Box 14, Volume 9)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1890 1896; 1890-1896 (Box 14, Volume 10)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1896 1912; 1896-1912 (Box 14, Volume 11)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1896 1899; 1896-1899 (Box 14, Volume 12)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1900 1905; 1900-1905 (Box 14, Volume 13)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1901-1902 (Box 14, Volume 14)
    - Benevolence financial records, 1905 1911; 1905-1911 (Box 11, Volume 6)
    - Benevolence committee records, 1953 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Little People's Mission, 1876 1881; 1876-1881; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains a single record book from the Little People's Mission group.
    - Little People's Mission records, 1876 1881; 1876-1881 (Box 12, Volume 12)
  - Furber Circle, 1883 1967; 1883-1967; 1 Folder; 6 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the records and correspondence of the Furber Society.
    - Furber Society records, 1883 1915; 1883-1915 (Box 13, Volume 1)
    - Furber Society records, 1883 1895; 1883-1895 (Box 13, Volume 2)
    - Furber Society records, 1896 1902; 1896-1902 (Box 13, Volume 3)
    - Furber Society records, 1903 1915; 1903-1915 (Box 13, Volume 4)
    - Furber Society correspondence, 1907 1918; 1907-1918 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Separated Materials
      Materials in this folder were removed from the Furber Society records, 1903-1915.
    - Furber Society records, 1916 1919; 1916-1919 (Box 13, Volume 5)
    - Furber Circle records, 1959 1967; 1959-1967 (Box 12, Volume 15)
  - Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor, 1887 1916; 1887-1916; 3 Folders; 5 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the records and bulletins of the Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor.
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1887 1891; 1887-1891 (Box 13, Volume 6)
    - Christian Endeavour Society bulletins, 1894 1896; 1894-1896 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1896 1916; 1896-1916 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1896 1901; 1896-1901 (Box 13, Volume 7)
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1897 1901; 1897-1901 (Box 13, Volume 8)
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1902 1905; 1902-1905 (Box 13, Volume 9)
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1904 1906; 1904-1906 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Materials in this folder were removed from Christian Endeavour Society records, 1902-1905
    - Christian Endeavour Society records, 1907 1913; 1907-1913 (Box 13, Volume 10)
  - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society, 1887 1918; 1887-1918; 3 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the records of the Ladies Foreign Missionary Society.
    - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society records, 1887 1898; 1887-1898 (Box 13, Volume 11)
    - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society records, 1899 1904; 1899-1904 (Box 13, Volume 12)
    - Ladies Foreign Missionary Society records, 1910 1918; 1910-1918 (Box 13, Volume 13)
  - Ladies Furnishing Committee, 1903 1906; 1903-1906; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains a record book from the Ladies Furnishing Committee.
    - Ladies Furnishing Committee records, 1903 1906; 1903-1906 (Box 12, Volume 13)
  - Kelsey Circle, 1938 1967; 1938-1967; 3 Folders
    This sub-series contains the records of the Kelsey Circle. Starting in 1962, some Kelsey Circle documents suggest that the group became a part of the Women's Benevolent Society, though it seems to have continued on as a largely independent group even after 1962.
    - Kelsey Circle records, 1936 1947; 1938-1947 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Kelsey Circle records, 1948 1955; 1948-1955 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Kelsey Circle records, 1956 1967; 1956-1967 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - The Men's Club, 1939 1953; 1939-1959; 4 Volumes
    This sub-series contains records from the Men's Club and includes a scrapbook, correspondence, and annual reports.
    - Men's Club scrapbook, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Men's Club correspondence, 1939 1940; 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Men's Club annual reports, 1939 1953; 1939-1953 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Men's Club records, 1942 1943; 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Friendly Service Committee, 1939 1972; 1939-1972; 4 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the records of the Friendly Service Committee which was originally known as the Sewing Committee.
    - Sewing Committee records, 1939 1942; 1939-1942 (Box 12, Volume 8)
    - Sewing Committee records, 1943 1947; 1943-1947 (Box 12, Volume 9)
    - Sewing Committee records, 1947 1957; 1947-1957 (Box 12, Volume 10)
    - Friendly Service Committee records, 1957 1972; 1957-1972 (Box 12, Volume 11)
  - Reading Committee, 1946 1960; 1946-1960; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains a volume of records from the Reading Committee.
    - Reading Committee records, 1946 1960; 1946-1960 (Box 12, Volume 14)
- Ministerial papers, 1741 1967; 1741-1967; 37 Folders; 9 Volumes
  This series contains papers, photographs, sermons, correspondence, diaries, and scrapbooks from the various ministers of the First Church in Newton.
  - Nathanael Appleton, 1741; 1 Folder
    This sub-series contains a sermon from Nathaniel Appleton.
    - Nathanael Appleton sermon, 1741 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Jonathan Homer, 1763 1834; 1763-1839; 3 Folders
    This sub-series contains the papers, sermons, and spiritual diary of Jonathan Homer.
    - Jonathan Homer sermons, 1763 1773; 1763-1773 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Jonathan Homer papers, 1791 1839; 1791-1839 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Jonathan Homer spiritual diary, 1809 1834; 1809-1834 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Daniel L. Furber, 1824 1899; 1824-1899; 7 Folders; 8 Volumes
    This sub-series contains the papers of Daniel L. Furber and includes collected sermons, correspondence, travel diaries, and photographs.
    - Daniel L. Furber collected sermons, 1824 1860; 1824-1860 (Box 16, Volume 11)
    - Daniel L. Furber collected sermons, 1861 1870; 1861-1870 (Box 17, Volume 1)
    - Daniel L. Furber collected sermons, 1871 1880; 1871-1880 (Box 17, Volume 2)
    - Daniel L. Furber collected sermons, 1881 1890; 1881-1890 (Box 17, Volume 3)
    - Daniel L. Furber collected sermons, 1891 1899; 1891-1899 (Box 17, Volume 4)
    - Daniel L. Furber papers, 1831 1859; 1831-1859 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Daniel L. Furber account book, 1850 1898; 1850-1898 (Box 16, Volume 8)
    - Daniel L. Furber travel diary, 1869 (Box 16, Volume 9)
    - Daniel L. Furber travel correspondence, 1869 1870; 1869-1870 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Daniel L. Furber travel diary, 1870 (Box 16, Volume 10)
    - James F. C. Hyde memorial address, 1898 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Daniel L. Furber funeral service materials, 1899 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Daniel L. Furber daguerreotypes, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Daniel L. Furber albumen prints, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Daniel L. Furber photographs, undated (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Theodore J. Holmes, 1883 1893; 1883-1893; 1 Folder; 1 Volume
    This sub-series contains sermons and a biographical sketch from Theodore J. Holmes.
    - Theodore J. Holmes sermons, 1883 1893; 1883-1893 (Box 16, Volume 12)
    - Theodore J. Holmes sermons and biographical sketch, 1883 1893; 1883-1893 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Edward M. Noyes, 1889 1941; 1889-1941; 14 Folders
    This sub-series contains sermons, papers, and correspondence from Edward M. Noyes. This sub-series also contains records about the Edward M. Noyes memorial window.
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1889 1900; 1889-1900 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1889 1900; 1889-1900 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1889 1910; 1889-1910 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1890 1902; 1890-1902 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1908 1917; 1908-1917 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1910 1918; 1910-1918 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1911 1918; 1911-1918 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1915 1916; 1915-1916 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1915 1916; 1915-1916 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1916 1917; 1916-1917 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Edward M. Noyes sermons, 1915 1921; 1915-1921 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Edward M. Noyes papers, 1894 1939; 1894-1939 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Edward M. Noyes memorial window, 1913 1941; 1913-1941 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Edward M. Noyes correspondence, 1938 1941; 1938-1941 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Jay T. Stocking, 1923 1936; 1923-1936; 3 Folders
    This sub-series contains sermons from Jay T. Stocking and also includes a memorial scrapbook for Jay T. Stocking.
    - Jay T. Stocking sermons, 1923 1936; 1923-1936 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Jay T. Stocking memorial scrapbook, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Jay T. Stocking scrapbook, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Dwight J. Bradley, 1928 1933; 1928-1933; 1 Folder
    This sub-series contains the papers of Dwight J. Bradley.
    - Dwight J. Bradley papers, 1928 1933; 1928-1933 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Morrison Russell Boynton, 1936 1954; 1936-1954; 4 Folders
    This sub-series contains the sermons and papers of Morrison Russell Boynton and also includes lectures and photographs.
    - Morrison Russell Boynton papers, 1936 1953; 1936-1953 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Morrison Russell Boynton sermons, 1939 1953; 1939-1953 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - M. Russell Boynton beach quiet hour lectures, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Morrison Russell Boynton photographs, 1954, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Nathanael M. Guptill, 1953 1958; 1953-1958; 1 Folder
    This sub-series contains the papers of Nathanael M. Guptill.
    - Nathanael M. Guptill papers, 1953 1958; 1953-1958 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Frank M. Weiskel, 1958 1967; 1958-1967; 2 Folders
    This sub-series contains the papers of Frank M. Weiskel.
    - Frank M. Weiskel papers, 1958 1967; 1958-1967 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Frank M. Weiskel sermons, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 18, Folder 20)
- Publications, 1841 1971; 1841-1971; 11 Folders; 10 Volumes
  This series contains calendars, bulletins, and other serial publications produced by the First Church in Newton.
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1841 1889; 1841-1889 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Church calendars, 1894 1898; 1894-1898 (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Church calendars, 1902 1903; 1902-1903 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Church calendars, 1899 1901; 1899-1901 (Box 21, Volume 1)
  - Church calendars, 1904 1905; 1904-1905 (Box 21, Volume 2)
  - Church calendars, 1906 1907; 1906-1907 (Box 21, Volume 3)
  - Church calendars, 1908 1909; 1908-1909 (Box 21, Volume 4)
  - Church calendars, 1910 1911; 1910-1911 (Box 21, Volume 5)
  - Church calendars, 1912 1914; 1912-1914 (Box 21, Volume 6)
  - Church calendars, 1915 1919; 1915-1919 (Box 21, Volume 7)
  - Church calendars, 1926 1968; 1926-1968 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1905 1971; 1905-1971 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - The Welcome, 1921 1923; 1921-1923 (Box 21, Volume 8)
  - The Welcome, 1923 1925; 1923-1925 (Box 21, Volume 9)
  - The Welcome, 1927 1929; 1927-1929 (Box 22, Volume 1)
  - Church news, 1939 1941; 1939-1941 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Church news, 1942 1944; 1942-1944 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Church news, 1945 1947; 1945-1947 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Church news, 1948 1951; 1948-1951 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Church news, 1951 1954; 1951-1954 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Church news, 1954 1967; 1954-1967 (Box 20)